Okay, we start today's דף, Daf, we're actually at the very top
of the דף Daf ט"ז עמוד א', Tet Zayin Amud Aleph, a
new משנה. Mishnah. Of course, we are still on פיגול, Pigul, which
we will continue to be on. And we are now going to
finally get to the משנה Mishnah that directly talks about מפגלין בחצי
מתיר. Maphgilin b'Chatzi Matir. So let's take a look. פיגל בקומץ ולא
בלבונה. Pigel b'Komatz velo bi'Levonah. So somebody is מפגל maphgel with the
קומץ. Komatz. Now this is the burning of the קומץ, Komatz, that's
okay, not the מיצה, Mitzah, which we will talk about very shortly
why that was not relevant. רש"י Rashi already raised it before. So
somebody does פיגול, Pigul, has a פיגול Pigul thought while he is
offering up the קומץ Komatz on the מזבח, Mizbeach, and not when
he is doing the לבונה. Levonah. בלבונה ולא בקומץ, Bi'Levonah velo ba'Komatz,
or the לבונה Levonah not the קומץ. Komatz. רבי מאיר אומר פיגול
וחייבין עליו כרת. Rabbi Meir omer Pigul ve'Chayavin alav Karet. It's פיגול
Pigul and you get כרת Karet if you eat it, the קרבן,
Korban, the
שירים. Shirayim. וחכמים אומרים אין בו כרת, Ve'Chachamim omrim ein bo Karet,
you do not get כרת Karet for the שירים, Shirayim, עד שיפגל
בכל המתיר, ad she'Yefagel be'chol ha'Matir, until you have פיגול Pigul for
the entire מתיר, Matir, which is why רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's position
is articulated as מפגלין בחצי מתיר, Maphgilin b'Chatzi Matir, as opposed to
כל המתיר, kol ha'Matir, חצי מתיר, Chatzi Matir, part of the מתיר.
Matir. So here it is the debate and even the term used
to describe it is in this משנה Mishnah or implicitly there. The
other thing to point out is although the חכמים Chachamim say it's
not פיגול, Pigul, אין בו כרת, ein bo Karet, presumably it's still
פסול, Pasul, and that was a point that the גמרא Gemara discussed
two
דפים dapim ago, that we do make these דרבננ'ס De'rabbanans of saying
פסול Pasul when it's happening, when it's close to being real פיגול.
Pigul. Okay, so here is that debate. The thought was only during
half of an act of what acts had to be done at
this time to get the קרבן Korban to the next stage. So
to get the שירים Shirayim to be able to be eaten, you
need to offer up both the קומץ Komatz and the לבונה, Levonah,
and this person only did one. That was half of the מתיר,
Matir, half of what was needed, and that was the debate now:
is a פיגול Pigul thought sufficient? Now ומודים חכמים לרבי מאיר במנחת
חוטא ובמנחת קנאות, u'Modim Chachamim le'Rabbi Meir bi'Minchat Choteh u'vi'Minchat Kenaot, the
חכמים Chachamim agree to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
with the מנחה Minchah for sin or a מנחה Minchah for a
סוטה, Sotah, שאם פיגל בקומץ, she'im Pigel ba'Komatz,
that if you had the פיגול Pigul thought just by the קומץ,
Komatz, because there only is a קומץ, Komatz, there's no לבונה, Levonah,
שהוא פיגול, she'hu Pigul, that the קרבן Korban is פיגול, וחייבין עליו
כרת pigul vechayavin alav kares, and you get כרת, Karet, שהקומץ הוא
המתיר, she'ha'Komatz hu ha'Matir, that the
קומץ Komatz is the מתיר Matir by itself. All you have is
the קומץ, Komatz, there's no לבונה, Levonah, and the קומץ Komatz allows
the שירים Shirayim to be eaten. So in that case you can
do פיגול Pigul, just by the קומץ. Komatz. They don't have anything
against the קומץ, Komatz, what they say is you need the whole
מתיר, Matir, and there it is the whole מתיר. Matir. And the
גמרא Gemara earlier said that that's obvious, and it was stated to
explain why even when it's a half of a מתיר, Matir, the
חכמים Chachamim would say that it's still פסול דרבנן Pasul De'rabbanan because
there are cases where something like this could be a דאורייתא פיגול
De'oraita Pigul when it is a מנחת קנאות Minchat Kenaot or מנחת
חוטא. Minchat Choteh. Okay, so that was the case of the קומץ
Komatz and the לבונה, Levonah, you need both to allow the remainder,
the שירים, Shirayim, to be eaten. Now we get also to one
of the beloved examples of the משנה Mishnah and the גמרא Gemara
about the שתי הלחם. shtei ha'Lechem. Where you need the two lambs.
שחט אחד מן הכבשים. Shachat echad min ha'Kevasim.
It's so funny, like I said, these two כבשים, Kevasim, they have
no, they get no credit, no recognition outside of the גמרא. Gemara.
But no play on שבועות, Shavuot, but in גמרא מנחות Gemara Menachot
they become a very nice example of חצי מתיר. Chatzi Matir.
Oh, I'm sorry, שבת Shabbos is שתי הלחם?
shtei ha'Lechem? That's also a שתי הלחם, shtei ha'Lechem, that's a different
שתי הלחם. shtei ha'Lechem. I meant the שתי הלחם shtei ha'Lechem of
שבועות. Shavuot.
So they're not talking about...
No, no, the שתי כבשים shtei ha'Kevasim is on שבועות Shavuot that
are מתיר Matir the שתי
הלחם.
shtei
ha'Lechem. Right, so that's what they're talking about.
I was wondering how the גמרא Gemara got there, maybe discussed yesterday
while I was elsewhere, because it says וכתם על הלחם, ve'Kitem al
Lechem, it sounds like the לחם Lechem should be מתיר Matir the
כבשים, Kevasim, not the other way around.
No, but that is true, that's why there's a difference between when
the גמרא Gemara said before כלל, klal, it's not a question of
what is conceived of as primary because you would say, yes, the
שתי הלחם shtei ha'Lechem is conceived of as primary, in order to
be able to have a שתי הלחם shtei ha'Lechem you have to
bring these קרבנות Korbanot because you don't bring לחם Lechem on the
מזבח, Mizbeach, חמץ chametz on the מזבח. Mizbeach. So it's true that
conceptually the שתי הלחם shtei ha'Lechem is primary, but in terms of
what allows it to raise to its proper level of קדושה, Kedushah,
what allows it to be eaten qua קרבן, Korban, it's the הקרבה
Hakravah of the שתי כבשים. shtei ha'Kevasim.
And you get that just because that's the standard...
Because that's what's מקריב makriv and that's right. There's probably some דרשות
Drashot as well, but you מקריב makriv the קרבן Korban and then
you eat the לחם. Lechem. So you're right, it's sort of like
think of it like a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach we said from the beginning of זבחים Zevachim that the אכילה
achilah is primary. Even though the אכילה achilah is primary, it only
gets to the level of קרבן פסח Korban Pesach through the זריקת
הדם. Zrikah hadam. So the question about what is sort of most
significant is not the same as the question of what's the מתיר.
Matir. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says: שחט אחד מן
הכבשים, Shachat echad min ha'Kevasim, לאכול שתי חלות למחר. le'echol shtei chalot
le'machar. So here's a case where the two מתירים, Matirs, you need
two things but they're the same thing. So you slaughtered one of
the two כבשים Kevasim to eat the two חלות challot of the
שתי הלחם shtei ha'Lechem of שבועות Shavuot the day after שבועות, Shavuot,
so it's a פיגול Pigul thought. Or הקטיר אחד מן הבזיכין hiktir
echad min habazichim לאכול שתי סדרים למחר, le'echol shtei sedarim lemachar, or
you had an intent when you were bringing one of the two
בזיכין bazichim of the לבונה, levonah, of the frankincense of the לחם
הפנים, lechem hapanim, again there you need to bring both, they're the
same thing, so you did one, a חצי מתיר chatzi matir with
the intent to eat the bread at the wrong time. So רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says פיגול Pigul וחייבין עליו כרת, ve'Chayavin alav Karet
same thing, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's a חצי מתיר chatzi
matir but I don't care, it's פיגול pigul and you get כרת,
kares, וחכמים אומרים אין בו כרת עד שיפגל בכל המתיר. vechachamim omrim
ein bo kares ad sheyipagel bechol hamatir. No, you need to have
the thought to the entire מתיר matir which would be both lambs
or both of the בזיכין bazichim of לבונה. levonah. Now שחט אחד
מן הכבשים לאכול הימנו למחר. shachat echad min hakvashim le'echol heimenu lemachar.
Now here's an interesting point why the lambs and the שתי הלחם
shtei halechem and the two lambs provide an interesting case study because
when you bring those two lambs on the one hand they are
a חצי מתיר chatzi matir each lamb in order for the bread.
The bread can only be eaten when the two lambs are brought.
But you're not only eating the bread, right? You slaughter the lamb
and what do you do? You eat the lamb itself, meaning it
is a שלמים. shlamim. So when you sprinkle the blood of the
lamb, it is a חצי מתיר chatzi matir for the bread and
it is a full מתיר matir for the lamb itself, right? When
you sprinkle the blood of the lamb you're now able to eat
the meat of the קרבן. korban. Okay,
so we've been talking about functioning as a חצי מתיר chatzi matir
when your thought was eating the bread at the wrong time. So
vis-a-vis the bread, if that was your פיגול pigul thought, one lamb
is only a חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. What if your thought is
about eating the meat at the wrong time? So let's take a
look. שחט אחד מן הכבשים לאכול הימנו למחר. shachat echad min hakvashim
le'echol heimenu lemachar. You slaughtered one lamb to eat from the lamb
tomorrow, so there it is, that's not a half of a מתיר,
matir, the עבודה avodah you do with this lamb is the whole
thing for the lamb. הוא פיגול וחברו כשר. hu pigul vachavero kasher.
That lamb is פיגול, pigul, the other lamb is of course fine.
You didn't affect the status of the lamb. לאכול מחברו למחר, le'echol
mechaveiro lemachar, if you thought at one lamb with the intent to
eat from the other lamb tomorrow, שניהם כשרים, shneihem ksheirim, they're both
כשר kasher because of the principle of אין מתיר מפגל מתיר. ein
matir mapagel matir. One lamb has no dependency on the other lamb.
The bread is dependent on both of them, but the lambs are
not dependent on one another. So this is I think why again
for the גמרא Gemara this is such a or the משנה Mishnah
an interesting case study, right? It's you get to look at it
all different perspectives. The lambs combined are a מתיר matir to the
bread so each lamb is only a חצי מתיר chatzi matir for
the bread. The lamb's relationship to the other lamb has no relationship,
so having a פיגול pigul thought for one lamb has no effect
on the other. The lamb to itself is the full עבודה, avodah,
the full מתיר. matir. So you have three nice cases from the
two lambs and the bread. Okay let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב, amar Rav, says רב, Rav, מחלוקת שנתן
את הקומץ בשתיקה ואת הלבונה במחשבה. machlokes shenatan es hakometz beshtika ve'es
halevonah bemachshava.
So this whole debate is when you had a חצי מתיר chatzi
matir was you did the קומץ kometz first, we're assuming you did
the קומץ kometz first although we learned before it's not necessary, you
did the קומץ kometz in silence without having a פיגול pigul thought
and you did the לבונה levonah with a פיגול pigul thought. Now
notice of course the concept of שתיקה shtika to מחשבה machshava gets
back to our old question whether the פיגול pigul thoughts are articulated
or not. It would have been much nicer if it would have
contrasted שתיקה shtika to אמירה, amira, but saying שתיקה shtika and מחשבה
machshava leaves open the question of whether the פיגול pigul thought is
articulated or not, with רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both say that
it is. Anyway, you did the קומץ kometz with no פיגול pigul
thought and the לבונה levonah you did with your פיגול pigul thought.
That's the debate, whether מפגלין בחצי מתיר. mapaglin bachatzi matir. אבל נתן
הקומץ
במחשבה, aval natan hakometz bemachshava, if the קומץ, kometz, again assuming you
do it first, you did it with your פיגול pigul thought, ואת
הלבונה בשתיקה ve'es halevonah beshtika and then the next act you did
in silence, דברי הכל פיגול, divrei hakol pigul,
everybody would say it's פיגול, pigul, that's not a case of חצי
מתיר. chatzi matir. Why not? שכל העושה על דעת ראשונה הוא עושה.
shekol ha'oseh al da'as rishona hu oseh.
Once you have said in your first act that you're doing this
for the intent to eat the bread tomorrow,
then any next act you done is assumed to be done with
the same mindset. So therefore it's not a חצי מתיר chatzi matir
because we assume unless you say otherwise that the second act was
done with the same intent and therefore it is a it is
a פיגול pigul with the entire מתיר. matir. Okay, so he's not
saying he's not changing the principle of the debate. The principle is
certainly that I said lamb I meant קומץ kometz and לבונה levonah
whatever same point. The principle is certainly whether מפגלין בחצי מתיר mapaglin
bachatzi matir and the חכמים Chachamim say you're not מפגל בחצי מתיר.
mapagel bachatzi matir. But what he's saying is if you articulate a
thought at the beginning, until you say otherwise we assume that thought
remains the entire process, כל העושה על דעת ראשונה הוא עושה kol
ha'oseh al da'as rishona hu oseh and therefore it would be what
do you call it and therefore it would be a case of
כל המתיר. kol hamatir. אבל שמואל aval Shmuel disagrees, ושמואל אומר עדיין
היא מחלוקת. uShmuel omer adayin hi machlokes.
No, not true, it's still a debate unless you have the thought
or you say it explicitly, we assume you are not doing the
second thing with the same intent as the first. I want to
say again that this points out that even רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot who say that פיגול pigul thought is articulated, it is still
very different from a speech act. If we... required פיגול Pigul to
be an act of making a statement, then you could not say
that your silence that followed, you said the same פיגול Pigul statement.
You didn't. The most we can say is that your second act
of silence was done with the same mindset. We can't say that
you've said the same thing. Okay, so that proves that at least
according to רב, Rav, presumably שמואל Shmuel as well, it's an issue
of mindset. It might need to be articulated at one stage, but
it's an issue of mindset. Now רב Rav says is, if you've
stated it initially, then even if your mind is blank afterwards, you've
said nothing, and let's even assume your mind is blank, we assume
that it is framed by your earlier statement. And שמואל Shmuel says
not true, and therefore this would still be a חצי מתיר. chatzi
matir. So basically all of the evidence is going to be like
שמואל, Shmuel, because, you know, there's nothing in the משנה, Mishnah, and
we'll see there's actually פשטות pashtus of a lot of other evidence
shows that it does not matter which was your first thought or
not.
Yeah, listing two things. I'm going to say the second point first,
since you... I was actually going to say the same thing. The
משנה Mishnah doesn't, you know, say anything one way or the other
about it. So, you know, don't see why there would be a
difference necessarily. But,
so we're still saying רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot can both be
right as long as at some point in the beginning, I guess,
you articulated it.
You know, then
what do you mean?
Meaning like, you know, you can't prove from this one way or
the other whether פיגול Pigul needs to be said or not still.
Right, correct. But what you can prove is that even if it
needs to be said, it's not about a speech act because it
wouldn't help to say כל העושה על דעת ראשון הוא עושה. kol
haoseh al da'at rishon hu oseh. That proves that it's about דעת.
da'at.
Well no, but you still have to articulate it. Right, right. It
is a speech act.
No, no, no. I'm making a difference between speech as an expression
of thought. In principle it's about thought, but we need the thought
to be articulated as opposed to a speech act, like an act
of מקדיש makdish something, okay, an act of קריאת התורה, Kriat HaTorah,
קריאת מגילה, Kriat Megillah, right, whatever. That's not about thinking but articulating
what you're thinking. It's about saying. So if we're about saying here,
you could not say that since I said it in the first,
I said it in the second. The most you could say is,
since I articulated what I was thinking in the first, right, then
it's clear that I'm thinking, continuing to think that or it's framed
as I'm thinking that in the second. Okay. So that is what...
so that's the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. We are
now one, two, three, four, five, six lines down from where the
גמרא Gemara begins, about probably about 15 lines down from the top
of the page, טז עמוד א, Tet Zayin Amud Aleph, and we
say איתמר מחלוקת. itmar machloket. So it's like a little א aleph
in half brackets, the רש"י א. Rashi Aleph. יתיב רבא וקאמר לה
להא שמעתא. Yativ Rava veka'amar lah le-ha shem'ata. רבא Rava was sitting
and telling over this debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. איתיביה
רב אחא בריה דרב הונא לרבא. Eitivieh Rav Aha brei de-Rav Huna
le-Rava. רב אחא בריה דרב הונא Rav Aha brei de-Rav Huna asked
to רבא. Rava. You know, by the way, I should just take
a second because we've been commenting a little bit about the whole
sort of oral culture and whatnot or like how these things were
learned. Right, it's not this huge debate of רב Rav and שמואל.
Shmuel. It's not like at this stage there's any... you know, there's
a lot to tell over. רב Rav says דעת ראשונה da'at rishonah
and שמואל Shmuel says no. So you imagine what was happening is,
he was telling it over for the purpose of having a discussion
about it, of like saying, is there a way we can prove
one side or the other side? Like that's how the tradition would
continue. Right, first you'd have a משנה Mishnah and then you'd discuss
the משנה, Mishnah, then you'd have certain statements of early אמוראים Amoraim
and you'd discuss them and you'd open it up for discussion and
debate. So he like opened this up for discussion and here we
are now going to start bringing the evidence. Okay, so רב אחא
בריה דרב הונא Rav Aha brei de-Rav Huna asked רבא. Rava. במה
דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, we have a תוספתא Tosefta that clarifies
this משנה. Mishnah. When is it that the קמיצה kmitzah alone, right,
the funny thing is, why until now when we were talking about
פיגול Pigul we always said the כהן Kohen does the קמיצה kmitzah
and he has this מחשבה, machshavah, he does the קמיצה kmitzah and
he has that מחשבה. machshavah. Why was that not an issue of
חצי מתיר? chatzi matir? It was only the קמיצה, kmitzah, what about
the לבונה? levonah? So the תוספתא Tosefta clarifies this point. Let's take
a look at the תוספתא. Tosefta. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim,
when is dealing with the קומץ komets sufficient and not a חצי
מתיר? chatzi matir? בקמיצה, Bikmitzah, when you do the קמיצה, kmitzah, ובמתן
כלי, uvmatan kli, and when you put the קמיצה kmitzah into the
כלי שרת, klei sharet, ובהילוך, uv'hiluch, and when you bring it towards
the מזבח. mizbeach. אבל באו להקטרה, Aval bau le-haktarah,
when it's coming the time to actually להקטיר le-haktir the קמיצה, kmitzah,
then הקטרת השירים, haktarat hashirayim, burn the קמיצה, kmitzah, it's only a
חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. נתן את הקומץ בשתיקה ואת הלבונה במחשבה, Natan
et hakomets bishtikah ve-et halevonah bemachshavah,
then the לבונה levonah matters. So if you gave the קומץ komets
in silence and the לבונה levonah with thought, את הקומץ במחשבה ואת
הלבונה בשתיקה, et hakomets bemachshavah ve-et halevonah bishtikah, or the קומץ komets
with the thought and the לבונה levonah in silence, so you only
had your פיגול Pigul thought with one of the two, that's where
you have the debate of the חכמים Chachamim and רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. רבי מאיר אומר פיגול וחייבים עליו כרת, Rabbi Meir omer Pigul
vechayavim alav karet, it's פיגול Pigul and you get כרת karet if
you eat it, וחכמים אומרים אין בו כרת עד שיפגל בכל המתיר.
vachachamim omrim ein bo karet ad sheyefagel bechol hamatir.
You have to have the thought in the whole מתיר. matir. Now
wait, wait, why other? I will tell you, I will tell you.
Before we get to why the גמרא Gemara brought this in to
debate רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, it's important to appreciate the very
important framing that this תוספתא Tosefta does for what we discussed before.
This תוספתא Tosefta is saying the whole discussion of חצי מתיר chatzi
matir is when you're burning the לבונה levonah and the קומץ. komets.
But when you're doing the earlier stages, we do not... Look at
the קומץ Kometz as half and the לבונה Levonah as the other
half. Why not? So there's two reasons.
One reason
is there's no such עבודה Avodah as doing קמיצה, Kmitzah, הילוך, Hiloch,
and מתן כלי Matan kli for the לבונה. Levonah. All the תורה
Torah says about the לבונה Levonah is it says you burn it
on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Okay, it does not say וקמץ משם מלא
קומצו ve-kamatz mi-sham melo kumto etc. So there—it's not an עבודה. Avodah.
So the only time it's functioning as an עבודה Avodah is at
the burning. Now, if you'll remember there was a discussion earlier, right,
about the gathering of the לבונה, Levonah, the ליקוט Liykut of the
לבונה, Levonah, was that an עבודה, Avodah, did that count as a
type of הילוך, Hiloch, the גמרא Gemara will discuss that momentarily. Okay,
but one explanation is just it's not even acknowledged as an עבודה.
Avodah.
But is it still חצי מתיר Chatzi matir because
if let's say you do the פיגול Piggul on the קומץ Kometz
but you still need the לבונה Levonah as a מתיר? Matir?
Right, but at this stage of doing קמיצה, Kmitzah, it's not—it's not
doing half of the job, it's only, you know, it's doing everything
that's needed at this stage. It's only sort of doing half,
but it's
not—are you מתיר Matir the שיריים? Shirayim? So that is the next
way to explain why the לבונה Levonah does not matter at this
stage, but it's like the flip of what Dov as suggested, is
what do we call something a מתיר Matir or not. The phrase
is not מפגלין בחצי עבודה. mepaglin be-chatzi avodah. The phrase is מפגלין
בחצי מתיר. mepaglin be-chatzi matir. The גמרא's Gemara going to discuss this—this
will be discussed explicitly later in the דף Daf but I'll just
say one point about it right now. So
מתיר Matir means that there's a focus on an effect that is
created. When I do the הילוך, Hiloch, let's say, of the קומץ,
Kometz, it's not having an effect yet. It's a necessary עבודה, Avodah,
but it's not yet creating a change of status. Okay, what creates
a change of status? The burning of the קומץ Kometz and the
לבונה Levonah effect the change of status of the שיריים. Shirayim. They
make the שיריים Shirayim מותר Mutar to be eaten. That's a חצי
מתיר. Chatzi matir. Anything that happens before is a necessary עבודה, Avodah,
but it's not a מתיר. Matir. So you can't say it only
did half the job if there's no job, if there's no—like it
didn't produce—it only produced half the desired effect. There is no desired
effect yet by the מתן כלי Matan kli and the הילוך, Hiloch,
the desired effect is only by the הקטרה. Haktarah. There you can
say, well this only did half of it, the other half has
to be done by the לבונה. Levonah. Okay, so that's two ways
of looking at it. One is downplay מתיר, Matir, speak about that
the עבודה Avodah needs to be done at this stage. The only
time the קומץ Kometz gets introduced as an עבודה Avodah is at
the what do you call it, is at the burning—I mean not
the קומץ, Kometz, the לבונה. Levonah. The other is to emphasize the
word מתיר Matir and to say that, you know, nothing is yet
being הותר Hutar until you get to the stage of burning it.
So the problem is not מפגלין בחצי עבודה, mepaglin be-chatzi avodah, the
problem is when you need two things to effect a change of
status and you're only doing one of them. And that only comes
at the time of הקטרה. Haktarah. We'll discuss that more later, there's
going to be an explicit discussion in the גמרא.
Gemara. So when they say במה דברים אמורים Bameh devarim amurim that
what?
במה דברים אמורים Bameh devarim amurim that a מחשבת פיגול machshavas piggul
by the קמיצה Kmitzah suffices and you don't care about the לבונה,
Levonah, that's for all the stages prior to
הקטרה: Haktarah: קמיצה, Kmitzah, מתן כלי, Matan kli, and הילוך. Hiloch. But
when you get to הקטרה Haktarah where the לבונה Levonah matters because
A, it's an עבודה Avodah there and B, it's a מתיר Matir
there, the two things I said before, in that stage now we
have an issue of חצי מתיר. Chatzi matir. And now we have
to say that if you only had the thought for one and
not the other, that's the debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and
the חכמים. Chachamim.
Okay, so you mean you can be מפגל mepaggel the קמיצה Kmitzah
all throughout
these—sure, all the earlier משניות Mishnayos said that you had a פיגול
Piggul thought at the קמיצה, Kmitzah, didn't mention the לבונה. Levonah. Why?
Because like I said, A, it wasn't yet a מתיר Matir and
B, because it was not—there was no yet עבודה Avodah for the
לבונה. Levonah.
So even if I had in mind to פיגול Piggul thoughts on
the לבונה Levonah makes no difference?
When you were being let's say מלקט Melaket the לבונה? Levonah? Yeah,
presumably because that's not an עבודה. Avodah. I mean we'll see later
whether there's an עבודה Avodah by the ליקוט Likut of לבונה. Levonah.
Right, and it feels kind of strange to say, you know, I'm
doing לבונה Levonah right now and what I think about it makes
no difference.
Well okay, but it's true about other things that are not considered
עבודות, Avodahs, right? I mean if you do something with the דם
Dam that wasn't an עבודה, Avodah, right? So alright, if you were
stirring the דם Dam and thinking thoughts, it wouldn't matter, that's non-עבודה
Avodah even though there's a reason you're stirring the דם. Dam. Okay,
so let's take a look. So we'll get back to—so this תוספתא
Tosefta brought to this debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel is
very central in appreciating the concept of חצי מתיר Chatzi matir and
we'll get back to it. But for now it's relevant to רב
Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Why is it relevant to רב Rav and
שמואל? Shmuel? Because the first half of it said what? The first—I
mean not the first half, when it got to the case of
מפגל בחצי מתיר mepaggel be-chatzi matir it says whether you put the
קומץ Kometz בשתיקה bish-tikah and then the לבונה Levonah or the קומץ
Kometz במחשבה be-machshavah and then the לבונה Levonah בשתיקה. bish-tikah. So you
see the debate applies even if you first had your thought and
then you were silent. Okay and that is the debate of רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir and the חכמים. Chachamim. That's a proof to שמואל
Shmuel against רב. Rav. It doesn't matter if you had the thought
first. So the גמרא Gemara says קתני מיהא, ktani mi-ha, so the
phrase קתני מיהא ktani mi-ha is... means I know there is more
to say about this תוספתא *Tosefta* and it was a very interesting
תוספתא *Tosefta*, but for now let's focus on the line that's relevant
for us, okay? So קתני מיהא *ktani miha* we taught nonetheless נתן
את הקומץ במחשבה ואת הלבונה בשתיקה *natan et ha-kometz be-machshava ve-et ha-levona
be-shtika* that the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* and
the חכמים Chachamim, *Chachamim* apply to a case where you did the
קומץ kometz *kometz* with your thought and then you did the לבונה
levonah *levona* in silence. So even though the thought was first, they're
still debating and we don't say כל העושה על דעת ראשונה הוא
עושה kol ha-oseh al da'as rishona hu oseh, *kol ha-oseh al da'at
rishona hu oseh*. פליגי *pleigi*, they still debate. So the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says אימא *eima*, okay, read it וכבר נעשה נתן את הלבונה
בשתיקה *u-kvar na'asa natan et ha-levona be-shtika* that you did the קומץ
komets *kometz* with your thought and you had already beforehand done the
לבונה levonah *levona* in silence, which means that you had your thought
with the קומץ komets *kometz*, but it came later rather than earlier.
So there's no palm reversing עבודות avodot.
*avodot*? Right, what we taught before that you can that you can
do the לבונה levonah *levona* before the קמיצה kmitzah *kmitza*.
But you can't be מפגל *mefagel* it retroactively.
Right, right,
but it's presenting the things out of order.
Right. Meaning what it should have said is you did the לבונה
levonah *levona* in silence and then the קומץ komets, במחשבה *kometz be-machshava*.
But it was phrasing it was mentioning the קומץ komets *kometz* first,
but in practice what it was describing was a case was that
the קומץ komets *kometz* was done second. Very difficult read of the
תוספתא *Tosefta*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not going to be happy.
Okay, so let's take a look. וכבר נתן את הלבונה בשתיקה מעיקרא
*u-kvar natan et ha-levona be-shtika me-ikara*. You had already done the לבונה
levonah, *levona* first and you had done it with silence. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says שתי תשובות בדבר *shtei tshuvot ba-davar*. One minute,
I can give you two
responses, two reasons to reject that answer. חדא *chada*, number one, דהיינו
קמייתא *de-hainu kama'ita*. Then it's not telling me anything more than the
first case. It already said your first act was done in silence
and your second act was done with your thought. So it's really
redundant. ועוד הא תניא אחר כך *ve-od ha tanya achar kach*. And
the ברייתא brayisa *braita* says and afterwards you did the לבונה levonah.
*levona* with שתיקה *shtika*, not before. Now of course that's not in
our ברייתא brayisa *braita*. Our ברייתא brayisa *braita* says את הקומץ במחשבה
ואת הלבונה בשתיקה *et ha-kometz be-machshava ve-et ha-levona be-shtika*. But they must
have had some ברייתא brayisa *braita* that said ואחר כך *ve-achar kach*
that you did the לבונה levonah? בשתיקה *levona be-shtika*. So it anyway
we have some ברייתא brayisa *braita* that explicitly says you did it
afterwards. So תרגמה רב Rav חנינא בבי דעות *Targema Rav Chanina be-vei
de'ot*. Okay, here how I'm going to defend רב Rav *Rav*. It's
talking about two intellects, meaning two people, two different people. So what
it means is you're right, we'll keep the order, we're not going
to fool around with the text of the תוספתא *Tosefta*. The first
one was done with a thought, the second was done in silence.
But you know why we don't say כל העושה על דעת ראשונה
kol ha'oseh al daas rishona, הוא עושה *kol ha-oseh al da'at rishona
hu oseh*? Because the first one was done with כהן kohen *kohen*
A and the second one was done with כהן Kohen *kohen* B.
So therefore you're not going to define כהן Kohen *kohen* B's thoughts
based on כהן Kohen. *kohen* A's thoughts. So in that case, that
would be a case of חצי מתיר chatzi matir, *chatzi matir* where
כהן *kohen* A did it with a פיגול pigul *pigul* thought and
כהן *kohen* B did it without the פיגול pigul *pigul* thought. Okay,
pretty weak answer, don't worry, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
continue to reject רב *Rav*.
Okay, so basically what they're
saying right now is that one
כהן *kohen*
can't mess up another person's acts essentially.
Well, no, חצי מתיר chatzi matir? *chatzi matir*. Meaning if I did
the קמיצה kmitzah *kmitza* with a פיגול pigul *pigul* thought, you're not
going to save me by having kosher thoughts for the rest of
it. But if I did a half of the מתיר matir. *matir*,
I did the קומץ komets *kometz* with a פיגול pigul. *pigul* thought
and we פוסק *pasken* like the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* that you need
to have פיגול pigul *pigul* with the whole מתיר matir *matir* and
you had it without that פיגול pigul? *pigul* thought, no פיגול pigul
*pigul*. But the same would be true if I had it without
the פיגול pigul *pigul* thought the second, the לבונה levonah *levona*. Because
here we're doing the thought was only for half a מתיר matir,
*matir*. You don't make it better. Okay, the only thing you do,
according to רב *Rav*, is you start with a clean slate. You
know, if you have no thought and I had a thought, so
in this case רב *Rav* would say my thought doesn't define you.
Okay, but in the end you not having a פיגול pigul *pigul*
thought is just as good as
if I had it without the פיגול pigul *pigul* thought. But this
raises an interesting question though, like let's say I'm a כהן *kohen*
and you know I have a על דעת daas, *al da'at* to
eat it tomorrow knowing full well I'm not going to be there
tomorrow.
Yeah, we've raised that question. We've I mean we went through all
of זבחים *Zevachim* and I even tried to find an answer to
this in the רמב"ם *Rambam* and I could not, which is and
even the מנחת חינוך *Minchat Chinuk*, you know, who is exactly the
question he would ask, which is what if the כהן *kohen* has
a מחשבה machshava. *machshava* to eat the שלמים *shlamim* tomorrow? He's not
the owner of the שלמים *shlamim*, right? Now at least when it
comes to the meat of a קרבן korban *korban*, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says that you divide up, you know, every single קרבן korban,
*korban* amongst all the כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim*. You don't just sort of
like lump all the קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* together and say here there
were 207 חטאות *chataot*, there's a hundred of you, each person take
two animals and we'll divide up the remaining seven. That would be
simple. No, you take each animal and you subdivide it according to
the number of כהנים *kohanim* and everybody gets a piece. So in
the end you will get a specific piece. But let's say you
had a מחשבה *machshava* to eat the leg of the קרבן korban
*korban* and you're not going to get the leg, you're going to
get the arm or something. Yeah, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* never discusses
the fact that you might not be in control of whether you
can actually eat this thing tomorrow. That is a question. I don't
know what the answer to that is. All right, let's keep on
going. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like בבי דעות *be-vei de'ot*. Okay,
now we are up to the תא שמע ta shma, *Ta shema*
about a third from the bottom with an asterisk at the beginning.
תא שמע *Ta shema*, come and hear, בדמים הניתנים על המזבח החיצון
אבל דמים הניתנים על המזבח הפנימי *be-damim ha-nitanim al ha-mizbe'ach ha-chitzon aval
damim ha-nitanim al ha-mizbe'ach ha-pnimai*.
So now this is... case on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, where you
sprinkle the
blood, you bring some קרבנות korbanot on the outside, but of course
the פר par and the שעיר se'ir you bring on the inside.
Now let's say a כהן has a פיגול pigul thought during some
of, not the first sprinkling of blood, but later. Now we know
by a קרבן korban. on the outside that after the first application
of blood, even for a
חטאת, chatas, it is... it's already good. It's done. So therefore a
פיגול pigul thought later does not affect its status. But by the
קרבנות that are brought inside, right, the פר par and שעיר se'ir
of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur every single application of blood is מעכב.
me'akev. So a פיגול pigul thought at any stage would be a
problem, okay? Would... could make פיגול. piggul Did they eat it? They
did not eat it. But you could still have... but that's true.
I mean the question would be, let's say you did eat it,
do you get כרת? kares? I mean you're true, halachically you... they
were not... they did not eat it, they burned it. But if
they did eat it, would they get כרת kares for פיגול piggul
would be the relevant question. Okay, but you're right, normally it would
not be eaten.
I mean if you eat it on יום כיפור Yom Kippur.
you get כרת kares for eating. There you go. Okay. במה דברים
אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, when is this true that after the first
application there's no longer פיגול? piggul בדמים הניתנין על המזבח
החיצון, Bedamim hanitanin al hamizbe'ach hachitzon, blood placed on the outer מזבח.
mizbe'ach. אבל דמים הניתנין על המזבח הפנימי, Aval damim hanitanin al hamizbe'ach
hapnimim, if they're placed on the inner מזבח. mizbe'ach. כגון, Kegon, for
example, מ"ג של יום הכיפורים, mem gimmel shel Yom HaKippurim, the 43
of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur, וי"א של פר כהן משיח מהוריות, ve-achas
esrei shel par kohen mashiach me-horayos, and the 11 of the פר
par of the כהן גדול kohen gadol from הוריות. Horayos. וי"א של
פר העלם דבר, ve-achas esrei shel par helam davar, 11 for the
פר par of העלם דבר helam davar that also from הוריות Horayos
for the ציבור. tzibbur. Now let's go through how you get those
numbers, it'll come up a little bit in the גמרא. Gemara
What?
For 11? It's for ציבור.
tzibbur. So let's do 11. Right, Michael is correct. The 11 for
the normal cases of these חטאות פנימיות, chatas pnimiyos, not יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur? it's seven towards the פרוכת paroches and four on the
four corners of the מזבח הזהב. mizbe'ach hazahav. That's 11. How do
you get 43 for יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur You get אחת achas and then seven and...
All right, Michael is way ahead of us all. So inside the
קודש הקודשים Kodesh Hakodashim there's eight, right? One up and seven down.
And there's פר par and שעיר se'ir done separately, that's 16. Then
you come out and you do it towards the פרוכת paroches separately,
that's 32.
Now, right
now, yeah, now
okay, that's 32. Now we... we're assuming that at this stage you
mix the bloods. So therefore we're not going to double it. So
there's the four corners and the seven on the top of the
מזבח הזהב mizbe'ach hazahav is another 11, 43. Okay. So for all
those applications...
So, פיגל בין בראשונה בין בשניה בין בשלישית, pigel bein berishona bein
beshniya bein beshlishis, whether you have פיגול piggul thought in the ראשונה,
rishona, the first stage, let's say in the קודש הקודשים, Kodesh Hakodashim,
the שניה, shniya, second stage on the פרוכת, paroches, or the שלישית,
shlishis, third stage which is on the מזבח הזהב. mizbe'ach hazahav. רבי
מאיר אומר פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת, Rabbi Meir omer pigul ve-chayavin alav
kares, it's פיגול piggul and you get כרת. kares. וחכמים אומרים אין
בו כרת עד שיפגל בכל המתיר. Ve-chachamim omrim ein bo kares ad
she-yepagel bechol hamatir. There, every application of blood is a חצי מתיר,
chatzi matir right? Because it's only going to be considered a זריקת
הדם zerikas hadam when you do all 43 applications. So according to
the חכמים, Chachamim there will be no פיגול piggul עד שיפגל בכל
המתיר. ad she-yepagel bechol hamatir. And according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir
it's enough that you had a פיגול piggul thought...
Meaning a פיגול piggul thought in every one of these...
Applications? Well, the question here is do you look at them as
sets? Because it says ראשונה, שניה, ושלישית. rishona, shniya, and shlishis. So
the simple way to understand ראשונה, שניה, ושלישית rishona, shniya, and shlishis
is first set, like קודש הקודשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, second set פרוכת, paroches,
third set מזבח הזהב. mizbe'ach hazahav. Although it could be just said
first sprinkling, second and third. So it's a little bit unclear. Meaning
what would רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say if I just had it
for one application of blood during the 11 or during the seven?
Would that be enough or would that even be less than a
חצי מתיר? chatzi matir Right, do you look at that as a
unit or not? That's not clear. It's discussed in רש"י Rashi and
תוספות. Tosafos. Okay. So anyway, here we see the same debate. ופליגי.
U'pligi. Now there it says, קתני מיהת, katanin mihat, we taught on
the left, מיהת, mihat, פיגל בין בראשונה בין בשניה בין בשלישית. pigel
bein berishona bein beshniya bein beshlishis. You had your פיגול piggul thought
whether the first step, the second set, or the third set. Meaning
so even if you had it at the first set, the חכמים
Chachamim would... ופליגי, u'pligi, and they still debate. Even though you had
the פיגול pigul thought originally, we don't say כל העושה על דעת
ראשונה kol ha'oseh al daas rishona. הוא עושה, it does not change
it. They debate just as much even if you had it at
the first set. Okay, so that's pretty clear against רב that we
do not say your later acts are defined by your first act.
Yes.
If where... if this means saying it out loud. The כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור going inside...
Right, who's hearing him there?
Right. So how... is it just...
Well, that raises my... if it doesn't mean saying it out loud,
that's a question about how do we know that this happened. You
know, let's say he just comes and he admits it. You know,
will we say okay, bring another קרבן, does he have נאמנות ne'emanus
or not נאמנות? ne'emanus? But you're right. I mean saying it out
loud just makes it possible to have a little more access, but
in this case, right, it's an excellent question. I mean how do
we know? Right, if somebody comes and he admits it, do we
say, oh you know, you're not נאמן, ne'eman, we don't believe you
that you did incorrectly? I don't know the answer to that.
Okay. But let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says, and here
we see evidence again like שמואל. Shmuel. So the גמרא Gemara says,
וכי תימא הכא נמי בשתי דעות, ve-chi teima hacha nami bishtei deyos,
you'll say that here too we're talking about two opinions. there were
two כהנים, so it wasn't defined by the earlier one. So what
happens? The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol did the first set with a
פיגול pigul thought in the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kadashim and he dropped
dead. You know, because he was thinking פיגול pigul in קדש קדשים.
Kodesh Kadashim. So then we brought a second כהן and he did,
you know, of the remains, so the thought of the first כהן
doesn't affect the other כהן. So that would be the scenario you
would try to give me, pretty crazy scenario. So the גמרא Gemara
says, הניחא למאן דאמר בפר ואפילו בדם משה פר. hani l'man de'amar
bipar v'afillu bedam moshe par.
That's good according to the opinion that says is בזאת יבוא אהרן
אל הקדש בפר בן בקר. v'zos yavo aharon el hakodesh bipar ben
bakar.
And there's an opinion that says אפילו בדם משה פר. afillu bedam
moshe par. What does that mean? The question is, what happens if
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol drops dead in the middle of the
עבודה avodah of the פר? par? And all you have now is
the blood. Can a new כהן גדול Kohen Gadol enter in without
bringing a live ox, enter in at the stage that all you
have is the blood of the ox? Or when you have a
new כהן גדול Kohen Gadol do you have to start afresh with
a new ox and start from the beginning? So if you say
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol can jump in in the middle, then
fine, you could create this crazy case of that the means he
had the thought and then somebody else took over. אלא למאן דאמר
בפר ולא בדם משה פר, ella l'man de'amar bipar v'lo bedam moshe
par, according to the opinion that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol needs
to start with an ox and if somebody died in the middle
you start again, מאי איכא למימר, mai ika l'meimar, what can you
say? Here it says you had your פיגול pigul, thought at the
beginning and they're still debating, so you see the debate, you know,
continues even in that applies even in that case. So אמר רבא,
amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan, what
are we talking about? כגון שפיגל בראשונה ושתק בשניה ופיגל בשלישית. kegon
shepigel barishona v'shatak bishniya u'pigel bishlishis. So it's not that he was
totally silent after the first one, then we would say על דעת
ראשונה הוא עושה, al daas rishona hu oseh, but he was had
a פיגול pigul thought on one, silence on stage two, and a
פיגול pigul thought on stage three. So you would say it's worse.
Yeah. But no, we're going to say it's better. דאמרינן, de'amrinan, we
would say, אי סלקא דעתך כל העושה על דעת ראשונה הוא עושה,
ei salka daatach kol ha'oseh al daas rishona hu oseh, if we
were to say that when you continue to do it you do
it by the original framing, מהדר פיגולי בשלישית למה לי? mehadar pigulei
bishlishis lamah li?
Why would he have bothered to have had that thought explicitly at
the third stage? Since he's bothering to think it or to say
it, it implicitly shows that that wasn't his thought during the second.
So that's how we could have a case where you had the
thought initially but it's still only חצי מתיר chatzi matir. because since
you didn't have it at the second, which normally we would say
is defined by the first, but then you did have it at
the third, it shows that the second was a different thought. So
the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רב אשי, matkif lah Rav Ashi,
so רב אשי Rav Ashi asked on this: מידי שתק קתני? mi
de'shatak tani? Doesn't say this crazy case: you did it the first
and you were quiet and then. It said בין בראשונה בין בשניה
בין בשלישית, bein barishona bein bishniya bein bishlishis, means you only did
it at the first, okay? So you can't read it like this.
אלא אמר רב אשי, ella amar Rav Ashi, so rather says רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan, what are we
talking about? כגון שפיגל בראשונה ובשניה. kegon shepigel barishona u'bishniya. Now, they
take out the word ובשלישית u'bishlishis or some have the גרסא girsah
of ושתק בשלישית. v'shatak bishlishis. You know, this is again one of
these crazy issues about about קדשים Kodshim
וזבחים, v'Zevachim, about, you know, these מסכתות masechtos and the text. So
I'll read it the way רש"י Rashi ותוספות v'Tosafos read it although
there are other texts and other ways to understand it, and you
had a פיגול pigul in the first and second thought and nothing
in the third thought. So that at least fits better the text
of the
ברייתא braita because the text would say then בין בראשונה בין בשניה
בין בשלישית bein barishona bein bishniya bein bishlishis doesn't mean a crazy
case of on, off, on, it means בין בראשונה bein barishona whether
you had it in the ראשונה rishona and the second or whether
you had it in the third, okay? So the case would be
that you had your thought in the first and second of the
sets and not in the third and then.
Wait, wait, just a second.
Well, one minute, and now let's see why we don't say כל
העושה kol ha'oseh על דעת ראשונה, דאמרינן de'amrinan we would say to
skip the word שלישית, shlishis, אי סלקא דעתך כל העושה על דעת
ראשונה הוא עושה, ei salka daatach kol ha'oseh al daas rishona hu
oseh, if really it would be defined by your first דעת, מהדר
פיגולי בשניה למה לי? mehadar pigulei bishniya lamah li? So again, take
out those little inconvenient words.
Why would you have bothered to have your thought by the שניה?
shniya? So it's the same principle, right? The principle is that this
idea of כל העושה is undermined if you bother to go back
and have the explicit thought again, okay? Because then we would say
then your silence actually means something else. But he's just saying that
to fit in the text of the ברייתא braita we'll say the
case was you had your thought on one and two and not
on three and in that case we would not say it's defined
by your earlier thought since you bothered to repeat it it shows
that silence really means a different.
You know that's not what the ברייתא Baraisa. is really saying.
Of course it's not what the ברייתא Baraisa is really saying. Let's
take a look. גמרא Gemara is finally going to end this discussion.
והא בין בין קתני, veha bein bein ktani, doesn't the ברייתא Baraisa
say whether the first or the second or the third, which means
any one of them is enough to be a scenario? גמרא Gemara
says קשיא, kashya, alright, that's true, it's a problem. So clearly all
of the evidence once more. So the debate of רבי מאיר Rebbe
Meir והחכמים v'hachachamim is whether מפגלין בחצי מתיר, mefaglin b'chatzi matir, if
you have your פיגול pigul thought only by half, רב tries to
say that if the פיגול pigul, thought was at the initial stage
the חכמים would say that that case we interpret it, we frame
it as if your thought was פיגול pigul throughout, כל העושה על
דעת ראשונה. All the evidence shows not that way, shows that the
חכמים *Chachamim* treat it as a חצי פיגול pigul *chatzi pigul*, as
a פיגול pigul בחצי מתיר matir? *pigul bichatzi matir* even when your
פיגול pigul *pigul* thought was original. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* tries
to get out of it, to re-read the case, to re-read the
ברייתא Baraisa *braita*, to say that when you have the thought explicitly
in more than one case, that's when we treat your silence as
significant. But all of the evidence is like שמואל *Shmuel* and against
רב *Rav*, that we do not say כל העושה על דעת ראשונה
הוא עושה *kol haoseh al da'at rishonah hu oseh*. As you could
imagine, this question becomes an important, interesting הלכה *halacha* question far beyond
פיגול pigul. *pigul*, right? Let's say we're engaged in I don't know,
some type of a business deal and I say something initially and
then something else comes up and I don't respond to it or
whatever. How much do we interpret כל העושה על דעת ראשונה הוא
עושה *kol haoseh al da'at rishonah hu oseh*? Normally we say דברים
שבלב אינם דברים *devarim shebalev einam devarim*, so I haven't articulated something,
you can't assume what I'm thinking, specifically in like two-sided deals, you
know.
But we also say like if it's דברים שבלב כל אדם *devarim
shebalev kol adam*, if it's self-evident what you mean, you know, even
if you didn't say it, it is relevant. Well, how much do
we think about כל העושה על דעת ראשונה הוא עושה *kol haoseh
al da'at rishonah hu oseh* and so on. So first is the
question about how do we rule. According to this, it seems like
we rule like שמואל *Shmuel* that it's not relevant. But then the
question becomes, is it not relevant specifically for פיגול pigul *pigul*, because
פיגול pigul *pigul* requires let's say, you know, has different parameters, maybe
really requires explicit thought or explicitly articulated thought, you know, but would
that apply also for other things as well? Not clear. Okay, but
this is the debate of רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* and all
the evidence is like שמואל *Shmuel* that your second sort of silence,
your silence afterwards is not defined by your earlier אמירה *amira*. Let's
take a look now at the going back to the issue that
we had quoted before, the important things we brought up in the
context of this debate. אמר מר *amar mar*, רבי מאיר אומר *Rabbi
Meir omer*, פיגול pigul. וחייבין עליו כרת *pigul vechayavin alav kares*. So
you get פיגול pigul *pigul* and you get כרת *kares*. So this
is in the case of all those bloods on יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*, all the inner sprinklings, not our משנה mishna *mishna*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מכדי *michdi*, let's see. כרת לא
מחייב עד שיקריבו כל המתירים *kares lo mechayev ad sheyakrivu kol hamatirim*.
You don't get פיגול pigul? *pigul*, forget the debate of רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים *Chachamim*, until you finish doing the עבודה
avodah. *avoda* properly, right? If I had a פיגול pigul *pigul* thought
in the שחיטה shechitah *shechita* and I stopped doing the קרבן
*korban*, if you did it חוץ למקומו
*chutz limkomo* and then חוץ לזמנו *chutz lizmano* or something or whatever,
right? Well, that's if you were, right, פסל *pasal* the קרבן *korban*,
but it's also even if you didn't finish the קרבן *korban*. If
I had a פיגול *pigul* thought at the שחיטה shechita *shechita* and
then I didn't bother doing זורק את הדם *zorek es hadam*, or
as Michael says, I was זורק את הדם *zorek es hadam* incorrectly
in the wrong place with another wrong thought, whatever it was, the
meat would not be פיגול *pigul*. For the meat to be פיגול
*pigul*, I have to finish the עבודה avodah *avoda* correctly. Okay? So
that's the principle עד שיקריבו כל המתירים *ad sheyakrivu kol hamatirim*, דאמר
מר *de'amar mar*, ירצה *yeiratzeh*. It says, you know, פיגול הוא לא
ירצה *pigul hu lo yeiratzeh*, it will not be find favor. So
we say it has to be in a context where it could
have found favor. הרצאת כשר kasher. כך הרצאת פסול *hartza'as kasher kach
hartza'as pasul*. The same way a כשר *kasher* finds favor is done
properly, so an animal that's פיגול *pigul* has to be done properly
other than the פיגול *pigul* problem, but it has to be finished
correctly, right? So that we all know, that's been a major theme
of פיגול *pigul*. So okay, where's this all going? הרצאת כשר עד
שיקריבו כל המתירים *hartza'as kasher ad sheyakrivu kol hamatirim*. The same way
an animal that's כשר *kasher*, you have to do all of the
stages that make it permissible, אף הרצאת פסול *af hartza'as pasul*, even
when the animal is פסול *pasul*, פיגול *pigul*, in order for it
to become פיגול *pigul*, עד שיקריבו כל המתירים *ad sheyakrivu kol hamatirim*.
All of the things that allow the animal to normally be כשר
*kasher* have to be done properly. Okay, so what's your question? והאי
*vehai*, this animal that let's say the כהן *kohen* had a פיגול
*pigul* thought with the blood when he was inside the קודש קדשים
Kodesh Kodashim, *kodesh kodashim*, כיון דחשב בה בפנים *keivan dechashav bah bifnim*,
once he had this thought in the inner sanctum of פיגול *pigul*,
פסלה *paslah*, he invalidated the blood. כי מטי בהיכל *ki mati beheichal*,
now he gets outside to the היכל Heichal, *heichal* and he's to
do the sprinkling on the פרוכת *paroches*, מיא בעלמא maya be'alma הוא
דקא מטי *maya be'alma hu deka mati*. It's like he's sprinkling water.
The blood is no longer כשר *kasher* and you're no longer doing
the עבודה avodah, *avoda* with a כשר קרבן *kasher korban*. Now of
course, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* jumps up and says, what the heck are
you talking about? If this is the way you were going to
look at it, nothing would ever be פיגול *pigul*, right? I שחט
*shachat* the קרבן *korban* and I have a פיגול *pigul* thought, so
the blood is now from a פיגול *pigul* animal. So now when
I get to do the זריקה *zarika*, I'm not, I'm doing זריקה
*zarika* on, you know, on מיא בעלמא *maya be'alma*. Right? All of
a sudden, this is your question?
So רש"י *Rashi* says that there it's a different עבודה avodah, *avoda*.
So what we're allowed to do, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes, I
mean obviously the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s just going to say, wait, there
being like a regular, I'll say. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to
in the end just say, ברק ליה *barak leih*. No, no, no.
The whole point is you bracket פיגול *pigul*, you ignore פיגול *pigul*,
you move it to a side, and then we say everything else
was done correctly. But at this stage, the way רש"י *Rashi* explains,
we're only prepared to say you bracket it when it was a
different עבודה avodah *avoda*. So if the שחיטה shechita *shechita* was done
incorrectly, I'm going to bracket the פיגול *pigul* problem and now when
I get on to קבלה kabalah, *kabala*, הולכה holacha? *holacha*, זריקה *zarika*,
I can pretend like it was no פיגול *pigul* to assess that
it was done properly. So yes, of course you bracket it. But
until now we're thinking you only bracket it when it's an earlier
עבודה avodah *avoda*. Here when it's the same דם dam *dam* that
you're in the middle of doing זורק *zorek*, you can't bracket the
פיגול *pigul* problem is what we're assuming, and therefore you have to
say if I did the first half of the דם *dam* with
a פיגול *pigul* thought. as I'm continuing with the דם, it's no
longer כשר. So I can't bracket and move it aside because the
problem came up in the middle of the process. That's what רש"י
understands the קשיא. kushya. The obvious answer will be that even here
you bracket it and you move it aside.
But then so the גמרא Gemara thinks that you can never have
פיגול in the middle of a process?
But when you have a middle of process? If you consider שחיטה
one act, זריקת הדם zerikat hadam normally is one application of blood,
right?
I guess if your thought is let's say,
well, I guess the point is what if you did it while
you're doing the הולכה? holacha What if you had it only for
half of the הולכה holacha? and not the whole הולכה? holacha? Right.
Would you is the גמרא Gemara now thinking that you have to
have the פיגול thought through the whole הולכה? holacha Maybe it is.
In the end, it's gonna give—it's always funny what exactly the question
is, because the answer is obvious. You bracket פיגול completely and you
then you look. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says, okay,
אמר רבא נסתפקא לה בארבעה פרים וארבעה שעירים. Amar Rava nistapka lah
bearba'ah parim ve'arba'ah se'irim. So one of these first crazy answers which
is: okay, you're right. What you would do is that you did
the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim it became פיגול, then you spilled the
blood. So then you brought another קרבן and then you did that
and then you had a פיגול thought there then you spilled that
blood, and so on. So therefore in that case, you're not doing
the next stage with מיא בעלמא because you're always getting fresh blood.
Alright. Moving
on, רבא אמר אפילו תימא פר אחד ושעיר אחד דיסקומי מרצי. Rava
amar afilu teima par echad vesair echad diskomi meratzi. For the פיגול
sake, it's מרצה. meratzeh. Which basically means: ignore the פיגול problem. When
we're trying to assess would this be מרצה, meratzeh, is it הרצאת
כשר כהרצאת פסול, hartza'at kasher kehartza'at pasul, we say: we mean besides
the פיגול problem. So if you bracket פיגול, you bracket it here
too, even if it's in the middle of an עבודה. avodah Okay,
so the answer was pretty obvious. It's a little question why the
גמרא Gemara got stuck.
I find the question very interesting that they're really—I know.
But then it has the types of issues you raised and תוספות
Tosafot suggests something else: one place versus two places. Maybe the גמרא
assumed that you could bracket it if it's all in—if it's all
in one place. But when you move from the קודש קדשים to
the היכל, a different place, maybe you can't bracket it. It's a
little unclear why it should have thought that. Anyway, now we have
a more technical problem. ארבעים ושלש. Arba'im veshalosh. We say there are
43 sprinklings. So the גמרא says, אה תניא ארבעים ושבע? ah tanya
arba'im vesheva? But we have a ברייתא Baraisa that says there were
47 sprinklings of blood on יום כפור. Yom Kippur. So the גמרא
says, לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא כמאן דאמר מערבין לקרנות הא כמאן
דאמר אין מערבין. ha keman de'amar me'arvin lekarnot ha keman de'amar ein
me'arvin. There's a debate whether you would mix the blood of the
פר par and the שעיר sair before the four קרנות, karnot, the
horns of the מזבח הזהב, mizbe'ach hazahav, or after you do the
four horns. Everybody agrees they would be mixed before you did the
seven on the top of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. But would they be
mixed before the four? So remember when we counted 43, it was
assuming that they would have been mixed before the four. If you
assume they were only mixed after the four, that gets you four
more applications: 47. והא תניא ארבעים ושמונה? Veha tanya arba'im veshmonah? We
have a ברייתא Baraisa, 48. Where does the extra one come from?
לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא כמאן דאמר שירים מעכבין הא כמאן דאמר
שירים אין מעכבין. ha keman de'amar shiyayim me'akvin ha keman de'amar shiyayim
ein me'akvin. There's a debate when we say the חטאות פנימיות, chata'ot
penimiyot, every single application of blood is מעכב. me'akeiv.
There's a regular debate of whether that applies to the spilling of
the remnant on the outer מזבח. mizbe'ach. On the one hand, it's
שירים, shiyayim, which is always considered to be not מעכב, me'akeiv, just
like a finishing up. And number two, it's on the outer מזבח.
mizbe'ach. And when we say it was מעכב, me'akeiv, it was everything
was on the inside. Nevertheless, there's an opinion that because it's an
inner חטאת, chatas, the שירים shiyayim are מעכבין. me'akvin. So according to
that opinion, it would be 48 applications of blood through which you
could have a פיגול thought. I mean, everybody agrees you'd have that
other application, but the question would be: would it be an application
that would be מעכב me'akeiv in which you could have a פיגול
thought? Now we are going to turn to the more central question
of why we've ignored the earlier stages of, you know, why by
קמיצה kmitza, and הולכה holacha. and קבלה, it was something that only—that
the לבונה levonah was not relevant for. Okay, and I told you
two ways of thinking about it, either that it was not an
עבודה avodah, of the לבונה levonah. at that stage, or because it
wasn't a מתיר. matir. Okay, so let's take a look at what
the גמרא says here. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. Three lines before the
lines get wide. So they raise the question: פיגול בהולכה מהו? pigul
beholacha mahu? You had a פיגול thought by the הולכה. holacha,
Now, why should that be different? Because remember what we said, we
raised the possibility that when you collect the לבונה levonah from on
top of the מנחה, mincha, that's an עבודה, avodah a זר zar
can't do it, even though the תורה Torah doesn't say it, doesn't
call it an עבודה, avodah it would be an עבודה avodah. and
would be categorized as הולכה, holacha. the גמרא said. It's an extra
עבודה avodah. and it's getting the לבונה levonah to the right place,
we'll call it a הולכה. holacha So if we assume that there
is a הולכה holacha of לבונה, levonah? now we have an interesting
question. You have הולכה holacha of the קומץ komets, and הולכה holacha,
of the לבונה. levonah So this stage of הולכה, holachah on the
one hand, it is there are two עבודות. avodos So do we
say that that's a... case of חצי מתיר chatzi matir because there's
an עבודה avodah of the קומץ komets and the לבונה? levonah. Or
do we say, so that would focus on עבודה, avodah there's another
parallel עבודה avodah. at this stage. Or do we say, it's not
a מתיר matir, yet. The מתיר, matir the thing that changes the
status of the שיריים shirayim is only the burning. So here is
exactly the question of why did we wait to discuss the burning.
Is it because earlier there is no עבודה avodah, of the לבונה
levonah? or is it because it's not yet a מתיר? matir And
now we're saying let's say there is an עבודה. avodah, Let's say
there is the הולכה holachah of the לבונה levonah is an עבודה.
avodah. So let's take a look. איבעיא להו: ibau lehu: פיגול בהולכה
מהו? pigul beholacha mahu? If you had a פיגול thought at the
time of הולכה holachah of the קומץ komets what's the story? אמר
רבי יוחנן: amar Rabi Yochanan: הולכה כקמיצה. holachah ke-kmitzah. It's like the
קמיצה kmitza, meaning we only care about the קומץ, komets we don't
care about the לבונה. levonah It's a total מתיר. matir ריש לקיש
אמר: Reish Lakish amar: הולכה כהקטרה. holachah ke-haktarah. It's like the הקטרה.
haktarah. Why? Because there's a הולכה holachah of the לבונה levona. and
therefore the הולכה holachah of the קומץ komets is only a חצי
מתיר. chatzi matir, Okay, so is that considered a חצי מתיר chatzi
matir? is a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan and ריש לקיש.
Reish Lakish. בשלמא לריש לקיש איכא נמי הולכה דלבונה. bishlama le-Reish Lakish
ika nami holachah de-levonah. We understand ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. There's a
הולכה holachah of לבונה levona based on our earlier discussion. So what
you do with the קומץ is only half the job. אלא לרבי
יוחנן מאי טעמא? ela le-Rabi Yochanan mai taama? What's the logic of
רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan assuming he agrees that there's a concept of
הולכה holachah of the
לבונה? levona. אמר רבא: amar Rava: קסבר רבי יוחנן, kasavar Rabi Yochanan,
כל עבודה שאינה מתרת, kol avodah she-eina materes, if you have an
עבודה avodah that is not a מתיר, matir. then
עבודה חשובה היא לפגל עליה בפני עצמה. avodah chashuvah hi le-paggel aleha
bifnei atzmah. It does the opposite of חצי מתיר, chatzi matir it's
less. But what it means is that normally we say, we've never
really introduced the logic of מתיר matir, as a central concept when
we talked about פיגול. What did we say? An עבודה avodah. that
is מעכב, meakev, right? So אי עבודה שנעשית, ei avodah she-naasis, even
though we don't say the הולכה holachah. has yet been מתיר matir,
anything. So what we normally say is it's a פיגול thought during
עבודה. avodah, So what רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan is saying is like
this: when all you focus on is a necessary
עבודה, avodah. that's its entire significance. So in the way you would
say it does less. But no, that means that's its entire identity.
So therefore, if you have פיגול during an עבודה, avodah you create
פיגול. There's no idea of it being half. This was the עבודה.
avodah. So what if there are other עבודות avodos to be done?
This is the עבודה avodah for this קומץ and I had a
פיגול thought during it. But when it works as a way to
produce an end result to be מתיר matir, the לחם lechem in
a way that reshapes how we think about it. We think about
the burning of the קומץ, not just or maybe not even primarily
as either one, as an עבודה. avodah We think of it as
the thing that's going to affect the change of status on the
שיריים. shirayim. It becomes defined primarily as a מתיר. matir As a
מתיר, matir. or maybe primarily, maybe additionally, but anyway as a מתיר,
matir. it's only doing half the job because in order to get
the שיריים shirayim to be able to be eaten you need another
thing to happen, you need the burning of the לבונה to happen.
So what he's saying is when all it is is an עבודה,
avoda. it's not being מתיר, matir then we say how do you
have פיגול? By having it during an עבודה. avoda. And therefore the
fact that there are other עבודות avodos? that are being done parallel
or whatever are irrelevant. But if it's effecting a change of status,
it's not about the process but it's about the result. It's effecting
a change of status, then we say it only is פיגול if
it has that other thing that it needs to effect the change
of status. Then it's only doing half of what it's intended to
be doing. Okay, so there is definitely a סברא svara here, I
know you could have said the opposite, but that is רבי יוחנן.
Rabi Yochanan. So he says when it's a מתיר matir we say
you can't have half of a מתיר. When it's an עבודה avoda.
alone, then it's not a half of anything, it's the עבודה.
avoda So when he says הולכה כקמיצה, holachah ke-kmitzah, so he's saying
and therefore we don't care about the לבונה.
So let's go back and ask, why did we only have this
debate by the burning, that we call it a חצי מתיר? chatzi
matir Why didn't we have this debate at the earlier stages of
the קומץ and the לבונה? So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would say
because there was no עבודה avoda by the לבונה except by הולכה.
holachah הולכה holachah there actually is an עבודה by the לבונה and
there actually it would be the same debate because you have a
parallel thing being done. רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan says no no no,
the whole idea of חצי מתיר chatzi matir. is מתיר. If the
only time that you say it's only doing half is when it's
actually effecting a change. And that only comes about at the burning.
Any earlier stage is not effecting a change and we don't look
at it as doing half.
I am very, I
am very attracted to רבי יוחנן.
Rabi Yochanan. When you say by change,
it changes the שיריים, shirayim, it makes the שיריים shirayim מותר באכילה.
mutar ba-achilah.
Okay.
Even though you say that הולכה holacha. is מתיר the next step
in the process, but it's not.
It just means it's a necessary process. It doesn't actually make an
object a different status. And now the גמרא is going to define
for רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan that מתיר has to be defined a
little more broadly, it doesn't just mean that it makes it מותר
mutar to be eaten, but it means it effects a change of
status. So let's take a look. Okay, I do too. Okay anyway,
אמר ליה אביי. amar lei Abaye. So אביי Abaye says, One minute,
on this plenty of cases that are not, that seem to be
the debate of חצי מתיר chatzi matir. that are not about something
becoming becoming מותר *mutar*. הרי שחיטת אחד מן הכבשים *hare shechitas echad
min hakvasim*, shechting one of the lambs, okay, and right, they effect,
and this is about the bread that comes with them, דעבודה שאינה
מתירתה *deavoda she'einah matirathah*, right, the שחיטה *shechita* does not make the
bread edible. When is the bread able to be eaten? The שתי
הלחם *shtei halechem* after the זריקת הדם zrikas hadam *zrikas hadam*, not
the שחיטת הדם *shechitas hadam*. So, ופליגי *u'pligi*, and they debate that
case even at the moment of שחיטה *shechita*, דתנן שחט אחד מן
הכבשים ועל שתי החלות למחר *detnan shachat echad min hakvasim v'al shtei
hachalos l'machar*, you slaughtered one of the lambs to eat the two
breads tomorrow. הקטיר אחד מן הבזיכין לאכול שתי הדר למחר *hikter echad
min habazichim l'achol shtei hadar l'machar* or the הקטרה haktara. *haktara* of
the הבזיכין *habazichim*. Now the הקטרה haktara *haktara* of the הבזיכין *habazichim*
actually is מתיר *matir* the bread, when you bring both of the
הבזיכין *habazichim* of לבונה *levonah*, the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*. But the
lambs, the שחיטה *shechita* isn't מתיר *matir* it, it's the זריקה *zrika*.
And nevertheless we say, רבי מאיר אומר פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת *Rabbi
Meir omer pigul v'chayavin alav kareis*, וחכמים אומרים אין בו כרת עד
שיפגל בכל המתיר *v'chachamim omrim ein bo kareis ad sheyefagel bechol hamatir*.
And חכמים *Chachamim* say that it was only half not whole. So
if we say that you really have to effect a change and
be מתיר *matir*, how did the שחיטה *shechita* of the lambs מתיר
*matir* the bread? You need the זריקה *zrika* to מתיר *matir*. So,
אמר ליה מי סברת לחם בתנור קדוש *amar lei misavras lechem batanur
kadosh*? No, no, no, it's not about becoming מותר *mutar*. It's about
effecting a status change. And the bread of the שתי הלחם *shtei
halechem* that come with the lambs is not fully sanctified, either not
sanctified at all or not fully sanctified by being baked in the
oven in the מקדש mekadesh *Mikdash*. שחיטת כבשים kvashim מקדשא ליה *shechitas
kvasim mikadsha lei*. The slaughtering of the lambs makes it קדוש *kadosh*.
It might be what it does is, we'll discuss this later, it
might be that it has קדושת דמים *kedushas damim* before the lambs
are slaughtered and קדושת הגוף *kedushas haguf* after the lambs are slaughtered.
But the point is, it effects a status change in the bread.
It brings the bread to the next level. דהבא לקדש כבא להתיר
דמי *deha ba l'kadesh k'ba l'hatir dami*. And if you're coming to
sanctify, it's like you're coming to מתיר *matir*, which basically means, I
mean, I love this approach, it says that it's about effecting a
status change. So however that status change is effected, that's where I
care, did if it only did half, it hasn't really done its
job. But if it's not about effecting a status change, then if
it did the stage of the process, it did the stage of
the process.
And we're trying to prove here רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*
right now, or,
we're trying to say that רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan* says
the debate, the concept of חצי מתיר chatzi matir. *chatzi matir* where
there's a debate, only exists, does not exist by עבודות *avodas* by
themselves, it only exists by an עבודה *avoda* that is effecting a
change. Okay, and so now we're saying, it's not so clear, we
find the debate sometimes by things that don't look like they're מתיר
*matir*.
And the answer is they are
מתיר *matir*, because מתיר *matir* doesn't just mean מותר *mutar*, מתיר *matir*
means effecting a status change. So now we're going to continue.
Wait, I just want to make sure I understand this. So what
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish*
says is anytime there's a parallel עבודה *avoda*, it has nothing to
do with whether it effects something. Okay? It just has to be
a parallel עבודה *avoda*. So there's a parallel עבודה *avoda* to the
lamb, which is the other lamb.
Okay, so that's why he would say it's חצי מתיר chatzi matir
*chatzi matir*.
And eventually they're going to affect the bread, but they don't have
to affect the bread right now, okay? Right, for ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish *Reish Lakish*, it's still about eventually effecting something else, but it's
not about changing the status at this moment for ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish *Reish Lakish*. Okay, מתיב רב שימי בר אשי *masiv Rav Shimi
bar Ashi*. So רב שימי בר אשי *Rav Shimi bar Ashi* asks,
אחרים אומרים *Acheirim omrim*, so this is about a thought you have
by קרבן פסח *korban pesach*, that הקדים מולים לערלים כשר *hikdim moolim
l'areilim kasher*, הקדים ערלים למולים פסול *hikdim areilim l'moolim pasul*. When you,
if you shecht the קרבן פסח *korban pesach* for people that are
ערל *arel*, כל ערל לא יאכל בו *kol arel lo yochal bo*,
you פסול *pasul* the קרבן פסח *korban pesach*. What if you had
two thoughts? So there's a debate there, and about which thought came
first and does it matter, and there's an opinion that if you
first thought about the people to eat the קרבן פסח *korban pesach*
who were the מולים *moolim* and then after as you were continuing
you thought about the ערלים *areilim*, then it's כשר *kasher*, but if
you did in the reverse and you thought about the ערלים *areilim*
first, it's פסול *pasul*. וקיימא לן דבחצי מתיר פליגי *v'kaiman lan d'bechatzi
matir pligi*. And over there in פסחים *Pesachim* we say they're debating
the issue of חצי מתיר chatzi matir *chatzi matir*. Now thankfully we
don't have to figure that out, right now the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't
elaborate and even רש"י *Rashi* doesn't elaborate, all we have to know
is that they're discussing שחיטת קרבן פסח *shechitas korban pesach* in the
context of חצי מתיר *chatzi matir*. So again the question is, שחיטת
קרבן פסח *shechitas korban pesach* is not yet מתיר *matir* the פסח
*pesach*, the פסח *pesach* is only הותר *hutar* when you sprinkle the
blood. Now the חצי מתיר *chatzi matir* of the שחיטה *shechita* is
one of the סימנים *simanim*, there's a trachea and the esophagus. So
the גמרא *Gemara* applies the debate of מפיגלין בחצי מתיר *mufagrin bechatzi
matir* even in it's, normally until now we've been having it in
these complex קרבנות *korbanos*, שתי בזיכין *shtei bazichin* שתי כבשים *shtei kvasim*,
קומץ ולבונה *kometz v'levonah*. But the גמרא *Gemara* actually applies it to
all animals, if you have the thought during the trachea and not
during the esophagus, or esophagus and not during the trachea, or whatever.
That's each one of those סימנים *simanim* is considered a חצי מתיר
*chatzi matir*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, why is it a מתיר
*matir*? It doesn't change the status of the קרבן *korban* until you
sprinkle the blood. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר ליה מי
סברת דם בצוואר בהמה קדוש *amar lei misavris dam betzavar beheima kadosh*?
No, who said it doesn't affect a change? Since when, what makes
you think that the דם *dam* in the animal's neck already is
at the right level of קדושה *kedusha*? דם סכין sakin מקדשא ליה
*dam sakim mikadsha lei*. The knife sanctifies the blood, the act of
שחיטה *shechita* brings the blood to the next stage where it now
can be offered on the מזבח mizbeach. *mizbeach*. So it actually adds
a level of sanctity to the blood, it effects the status of
the blood. דהבא לקדש כבא להתיר דמי *deha ba l'kadesh k'ba l'hatir
dami*. What's amazing about this גמרא is in this discussion of מפסלין
בחצי מתיר mifaslin bechatzi matir in the debate of רבי יוחנן Rebbe
Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish. we're finding out the most we
have ever found out about how the stages effect the status of
the קרבן. Also, by the way, the idea that the סכין sakin
is מקדש lends a lot of credence to the idea that you
need the סכין to be a כלי שרת, kli shares, which is
a debate of the ראשונים. Rishonim. So now the גמרא says תא
שמע, come and hear.
במה דברים אמורים בקמיצה ובמתן כלי ובהילוך. Bameh devarim amurim bikmitza uvimatan
kli uvehiluch. That was the ברייתא. Baraisa That when it's talking about
קמיצה, kmitza putting in the כלי kli and הילוך, hiluch, there you
don't have to worry about the לבונה. You only have to worry
about the לבונה by at the end. So this seems actually to
be a support for רבי יוחנן. Rebbe Yochanan.
מאי לאו הילוך דהקטרה? Mai lav hiluch de'haktara? So you see, even
though you're doing the הילוך hiluch to eventually burn it, you do
not have to worry about the לבונה. That supports רבי יוחנן Rebbe
Yochanan for once. So the גמרא says לא הילוך דמתן כלי. lo
hiluch dematan kli. We're not talking about the הילוך hiluch to burn
it, we're talking about when you take the קומץ from the vessel
and you're moving it to put it into the כלי שרת. kli
shares. So that's like a הילוך hiluch that's not an עבודה. We're
not talking about the הילוך hiluch of going to actually burn it.
So the גמרא says one minute. אי הכי במתן כלי ובהילוך. Ei
hachi bimatan kli uvehiluch. It shouldn't say that whether you put it
in the vessel or the הילוך, hiluch, which suggests the הילוך hiluch
that comes after the קומץ has been put in the vessel and
bringing it to the מזבח. בהילוך ובמתן כלי מיבעי ליה. Behiluch uvimatan
kli mibaei lei. The order should have been reversed if it was
talking about the הילוך hiluch that preceded the putting it in the
vessel. So the גמרא says הא לא קשיא, ha lo kashya, that's
not
difficult. תני הכי. Tani hachi. Have it say
that. But I'm still not satisfied. בא לו להקטרה. Ba lo lehaktara.
The ברייתא continues that says if you put it in the
כלי kli and then you did the הילוך hiluch and then you
came to burn it. So according to you, it should have said
בא לו להולכה מיבעי ליה. ba lo leholacha mibaei lei. That after
you put it in the כלי, kli, then there was a הולכה.
holacha Because what it's basically saying is look, we had the ברייתא
before which got us all excited that says there's no debate prior
to the הקטרה. haktara. If it's the קמיצה, the מתן כלי, matan
kli, the הילוך, hiluch, no debate. The whole debate is by the
burning, that's when you have a חצי מתיר. So that's strong evidence
to רבי יוחנן. Rebbe Yochanan That seems to say that there's no
stage prior to the burning that would be considered a חצי מתיר.
How does ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, get out of this? So the
way ריש לקיש was trying to get out of this is by
saying we're not talking about the הילוך. hiluch. When it says הילוך,
hiluch, we're talking about getting it from the מנחה mincha into the
כלי. kli. But we're not actually talking about the הילוך hiluch that's
a real עבודה. So the גמרא is basically saying first of all,
it mentions הילוך hiluch after the מתן כלי, matan kli, which sounds
like the הילוך hiluch that's the real עבודה. Second of all, according
to you, the ברייתא should have said that at the stage of
הילוך, hiluch, that's when there's an issue of חצי מתיר. Why didn't
the ברייתא say that? בא לו להולכה מיבעי ליה. Ba lo leholacha
mibaei lei. It should have said when you come to the stage
of הילוך, hiluch, that's the issue of חצי מתיר according to ריש
לקיש. So the גמרא says הא לא קשיא, ha lo kashya, that's
not difficult. כיון דהולכה צורך הקטרה היא, keivan deholacha tsorech haktara hi,
since it's leading up to הקטרה haktara, and necessary, קרי ליה הקטרה.
kari lei haktara. It refers to it as הקטרה. haktara, But when
it's saying the debate of רבי מאיר and the חכמים is by
הקטרה, haktara it doesn't just mean הקטרה, haktara, it means הקטרה haktara.
and הילוך. hiluch. Again, a pretty bad answer. אלא נתן את הקומץ
בשתיקה, Ela natan es hakomets beshtika, but no, let's go back to
it said the משנה or the ברייתא, it said if you put
the קומץ in silence. According to you, ריש לקיש, it should have
said הוליך מיבעי ליה, holich mibaei lei, if you did the הולכה
holacha in silence and the other הולכה was with a מחשבה. קשיא.
Kashya. It's difficult. So actually the strong evidence of that ברייתא is
and is like רבי יוחנן that the only debate is by the
קמיצה and this is a great conceptual question of what is the
idea, how do we think of the עבודות? Are they just necessary
or after an עבודה it actually effects a status change? And רבי
יוחנן says the idea of חצי מתיר is only when it effects
a change because then you could say that it was working in
conjunction with something else and it has to do the whole job.
And therefore if it only did half the job, it's not yet
significant. And that then forces us to think which עבודה effects a
change right away. They all eventually effect the change, but which effects
a change right away? And we said not only at the end
of the process, the זריקת הדם and the הקטרה, haktara but even
some things at the beginning of the process like the שחיטה raises
the דם to the next
level. The שחיטה of the כבשים raises the bread to the next
level and so on. We will have to end here.
But in terms of a מנחה mincha it's just the הקטרה.
In terms of a מנחה, mincha, it would just be the הקטרה
effects the שירים. shirayim. No earlier stage changes statuses in conjunction with
something
else.